Finding Aid for First Unitarian Universalist Church of Ann Arbor Records 1865-1997 and 2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First Unitarian Universalist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1865-1997 2007
First Unitarian Universalist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Founded in 1865, the First Unitarian Universalist Church of Ann Arbor has a history of social activism and involvement with the University of Michigan community. The records contain church files and annual reports, sermons and correspondence of church ministers, and church publications--including the weekly newsletter.
86918 Ba 2
9 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group has come to the library in several different accessions beginning in 1972. Donor No. 5319
The record group is open for research.
In 1865, forty Ann Arborites invited Charles Brigham (1865-1877) from Massachusetts to become the first minister for the newly organized First Unitarian Church. Services were originally conducted at the old Court House but in 1867 the church purchased a building at Fourth and Ann Street. In 1882, under the ministry of Jabez Sunderland (1878-1898), a new Romanesque church was built at State and Huron Street, near the University of Michigan campus. The church would remain there until 1946 when the congregation purchased the Dr. Dean Myers home at 1917 Washtenaw Avenue. An addition was added to that residence in 1956. In 1995, the congregation began plans to build a new church, which was completed in 1999 on Ann Arbor-Saline Road at the corner of Ellsworth.
Throughout its history the church has been identified with the liberal religious tradition and has maintained close ties with the university community. In the 1880s, Minister Sunderland was attracted by religious movements in India and argued strongly for Indian independence. His wife, Eliza, was one of the first women to earn a doctorate from the University of Michigan and later went on to become a prominent educator and suffragist.
During the depression of the 1930s, Minister Harold P. Marley (1920-1942) was involved in a range of social issues. He was an active member of the American Civil Liberties Union and the church doors remained open for labor union meetings and controversial speakers who sometimes could obtain no other meeting place in Ann Arbor. An editorial in the student-run Michigan Daily in 1937 noted that this church is "a center of activity in behalf of true democracy... and a genuine force in our social thinking."
During World War II, the church was involved in providing human services for the influx of workers to the Willow Run bomber plant. Gilbert House in Ypsilanti was established to meet these needs. In the 1950s, Minister Edward Redman (1943-1960) was also active in his opposition to McCarthyism through his writings and participation in various organizations.
In the 1960s, the church with its new minister Erwin A. Gaede (1961-1979), supported the civil rights movement as well as the new women's movement. The Vietnam war, however, proved more divisive and eventually some members of the congregation chose to leave the church over this issue. Gaede counseled and wrote letters for those men applying for conscientious objector status during the Vietnam war, and remained visible in the community as a proponent of peace through his letters to the editors of various newspapers.
During this time, as well, (1969-1971) the Black Economic Development League and the Welfare Rights Organization (BEDL-WRO) were petitioning and demonstrating in area churches in the spirit of the Black Manifesto, to the effect that traditionally white congregations owed the league and the area's poor population financial support, and demanded $10,000 in cash and $21,000 in stocks from First Unitarian of Ann Arbor. The congregation was among the first to attempt to meet the demands.
In 1980, the church added "Universalist" to its name in a spirit of consolidation between two similar religious traditions. Today, the Ann Arbor church is one of 1,000 Unitarian-Universalist congregations nationally which include close to 200,000 members. In explaining the beliefs of the church, the current minister of the Ann Arbor church, Kenneth W. Phifer (1980-present) has written, "Unitarian-Universalism is a religion based on the freedom of individuals to determine their own religious understanding, tolerance of others whose conclusions are different, and dependence upon reason in considering the meaning of life. The fundamental theology is that all reality forms a unified whole to which we owe respect and love."
The records of the First Unitarian-Universalist Church of Ann Arbor have been divided into seven series: Church History, Record Books; Church Reports; Yearly Files; Church Publications; Topical Files; and Ministers' Files.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Unitarian Universalist churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Women--Religious life--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Brigham, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1820-1879.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; First Unitarian Universalist Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Marley, Harold Parsons.; Unitarian Universalist churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.
Contributors:
Brigham, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1820-1879.; Gaede, Erwin A.; Marley, Harold Parsons.; Redman, Edward H.; Sunderland, Jabez Thomas, 1842-1936.
Genre/Form:
Sermons.; Photographs.
- Church History
  The history of the church is well documented. The series Church History includes brief histories prepared for various events in the life of the church and two anonymous histories believed authored by former ministers. More formal histories include the 1985 account by Minister Edward H. Redman of his own ministry to the church, and a comprehensive 1990 history by congregation member Marjorie Reade entitled, "The Story of Our First Hundred Years." Included in the series material are the notes and correspondence of Marjorie Reade with fellow congregation-member Ruth Bordin concerning the history of the church, and between Marjorie Reade and Alice Sunderland Wethey, granddaughter of Minister Jabez Sunderland, concerning the history of the Sunderland family. Also included are notes and correspondence regarding the sharing of church history with other organizations, including the national Unitarian Universalist Historical Society. The series concludes with articles and letters of recognition concerning the church's 1990 125th anniversary celebration.
  - Ann Arbor Magazine, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Anonymous Histories 1883-circa 1990 (Box 1)
  - Celebration of the Living Church 1982 (Box 1)
  - Church Property (Box 1)
    (includes 2 undated reports regarding history and maintenance and undated landscape architecture plan)
  - Constitution, By-Laws, Directories, and General Information 1944-1980 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Correspondence Regarding Church History 1987-1994 (Box 1)
  - Notes and Correspondence of Ruth Bordin and Marjorie Reade (regarding church history) 1984-1989 (Box 1)
  - Notes and Correspondence of Alice Sunderland Wethey and Marjorie Reade (regarding Sunderland history) 1990 (Box 1)
  - Recollection of the Ministry to the First Unitarian Church of Ann Arbor of Rev. Edward Homer Redman 1943-1960, 1985 (Box 1)
  - The Story of Our First Hundred Years, by Marjorie Reade, 1990 (Box 1)
  - History by Marjorie Reade 1965-1980 (Box 1)
  - 125th Anniversary celebration miscellaneous (1990) (Box 1)
  - Things remembered ..., Thomas G. Overmire, ed., 1998 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    (portraits, church gatherings and church building)
- Church Record Books
  The Record Books are general compilations of church records, containing budget information, lists of church members, and minutes of the board of trustees. These early general summaries of church events and records are continued in function by the later Yearly File series.
  - Annual Record Books
    - 1867-January 1901 (Box 1)
    - January 1901-January 1912 (Box 1)
    - January 1912-May 1935 (Box 1)
    - June 1935-September 1948 (Box 1)
    - October 1948-June 1952 (Box 1)
      (1952-1986 continued as part of Yearly File series)
  - Scrapbook 1906-1924 (Box 1)
    (bulletins, newspaper clippings, and "Unitarian Calendars")
  - Treasurer's Book (Box 2)
    - January 1900-April 1908 (Box 2)
    - May 1908-January 1915 (Box 2)
- Church Reports 1948-1997
  The Church Reports series includes the Annual Reports (1948-1997), originally called Annual Proceedings, then Yearbook, which became semi-annual reports in 1974. These reports contain the minutes of the annual meeting and yearly reports from various church committees and organizations. Researchers seeking specific groups and committee reports, particularly for early organizations, should also look in the Topical Files series.
  - Annual Reports 1948-1997, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (incomplete)
  - Miscellaneous Reports 1888-1889 (Box 2)
    (minister's, Unity Club, King's Daughters Ladies Union, Sunday School)
- Yearly File 1859-1979
  The Yearly File includes minutes, mailings, budget miscellanea, and occasional correspondence. These files are most complete for the period 1956-1973 but scattered files exist before and after that period.
  - 1859-1940 (Box 2)
  - 1941-1955 (Box 2)
  - 1956-1965, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - 1967-1973, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - 1974-1979 (scattered) (Box 3)
- Church Publications 1880-1997
  Church Publications are arranged chronologically and include flyers, bulletins, newsletters and orders of service. The newsletter provides a good overview of church activities and frequently includes writings by the minister.
  - Directories 1964-1997 (extremely scattered) (Box 3)
  - Flyers, Bulletins and Mailings
    - 1880-1899 (Box 3)
    - 1900-1919 (Box 3)
    - 1920-1929 (Box 3)
    - 1930-1939 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous circa 1908-1996, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - 1928-1929 (Box 3)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 3)
    - 1932-1936 (Box 3)
    - 1949-1956 (Box 3)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1975, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - 1976-1983, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - 1984-1990 (scattered) (Box 4)
  - Order of Service
    - 1959-1961 (Box 4)
    - 1966-1971, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1974-1989 (Box 4)
  - Wheels Within Wheels: Manual on Organizational Structure and Procedures of First Unitarian Church of Ann Arbor, undated (Box 4)
- Topical Files 1923-1989
  Topical Files include material on various church organizations as well as important church events. "Adult Discussion Group, 1966-1970" and "Minister Review (Edwin Gaede), 1972" document the political climate of the church during the Vietnam war. "Unity Hall Lectures, 1933-1942" includes only a few copies of lectures but this file shows evidence of the wide range of labor and political groups which used the hall during this period. Surveys and questionnaires and their resulting reports can be found in the files, "Minister Search, Pulpit Committee, 1960-1961" and "Committees and Other Church Organizations, Questionnaire Committee, 1966" and in the Minister Search information packets of 1979 and 1994. These information packets were sent to prospective candidates for minister and assistant minister, respectively, and contain various publications, photographs, sermons and reports. They offer to the researcher broad overviews of the climate and activities of the church.
  Other church groups represented in this series can be found in the Committees subseries, including the Social Action Committee, which had a BEDL-WRO subcommittee, and the Long Range Planning Committee, also called the Development Committee. The BEDL-WRO subcommittee file contains audio tapes of the 1970 appeal to the congregation by Charles Thomas Jr. for "reparation" to African-Americans. Also included in the Committee subseries are the financial records of the Jackson Fund, a substantial endowment, made by congregation members George L. and Florence Hazelton Jackson in 1955, which has continued to provide funding throughout the years to the church via investment returns.
  - Adult Discussion Group 1966-1970 (Box 4)
  - American Unitarian Youth 1946-1948 (Box 4)
  - Anniversary and Dedication Celebrations 1941-1989 (Box 4)
  - Article of Incorporation 1955 (Box 4)
  - Art Objects 1960-1968 (Box 4)
  - Building Campaign
    - 1945 (includes plans) (Box 4)
    - 1952 (includes blueprints) (Box 4)
  - Celebration of Living Church 1982 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of Recognition circa 1980s (Box 4)
  - Certificates of Dedication 1950-1959 (Box 4)
  - Church Attendance 1944-1948 (Box 4)
  - Church Library 1923-1936 (Box 4)
  - Committees and Other Church Organizations
    - 1990 Committee 1988-1990 (Box 4)
    - Board of Trustees 1967-1979 (Box 4)
    - Committee Personnel 1945-1956 (Box 4)
    - Denominational Affairs Committee 1956-1976 (Box 4)
    - Endowment Fund Advisory Committee 1970-1974 (Box 4)
    - Finance Committee 1958-1977 (Box 4)
    - Hospitality Committee 1957-1959 (Box 4)
    - Investment Committee 1955-1959 (Box 4)
    - Jackson Social Welfare Committee 1961-1974 (Box 4)
    - Liberal Religious Youth 1954-1959 (Box 5)
    - Long Range Planning Committee
      - Miscellaneous 1952-1964 (Box 5)
      - Reports and Minutes 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - Membership Committee 1958-1976 (Box 5)
    - Merger Committee 1958-1959 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous committees 1954-1979 (Box 5)
    - Music Department 1956-1977 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter Committee 1956-1959, undated (Box 5)
    - Project Transition circa 1971 (Box 5)
    - Public Relations Committee (Promotion Committee) 1956-1957 (Box 5)
    - Questionnaire Committee 1966 (Box 5)
    - Religious Education 1976-1980, undated (Box 5)
    - Social Action Committee
      - 1962-1973 (Box 5)
      - BEDL-WRO (Black Economic Development League-Welfare Rights Organization)
        - Miscellaneous 1969-1971 (Box 5)
        - Audio tapes of November 23, 1970 appeal with index to tapes and other notes (Box 5)
  - Conscientious Objector Statements 1967 (Box 5)
  - Finances
    - Audit Reports 1960, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Budgets 1951-1974 (Box 5)
    - Canvass
      - 1958-1960 (Box 5)
      - 1966-1971 (Box 5)
      - 1971-1980 (Box 5)
    - Jackson Funds 1955-1990 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1956-1982 (Box 5)
      (includes correspondence)
  - First Unitarian Society Reports 1885-1903 (Box 5)
  - Laymen's League 1920-1942, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Minister Review (Edwin Gaede) 1972 (Box 5)
  - Minister Search
    - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Information Packets
      - 1979 (Box 5)
      - 1994 (Box 5)
      - 2007 (Box 5)
        (includes compact disk)
    - Pulpit Committee
      - 1960-1961 (Box 6)
      - Notebook 1960-1961 (Box 6)
  - Reed Stuart (In Memoriam: Reed Stuart), 1910 (Box 6)
  - Religious Education
    - 1960-1965 (Box 6)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 6)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 6)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 6)
  - Unitarian Ministers Association 1948-1953 (Box 6)
  - Unity Club Secretary's Book 1893-1900 (Box 6)
  - Unity Hall Lectures 1933-1942 (Box 6)
  - University Student Outreach 1931-1954 (Box 6)
  - Universalist Conventions of Michigan
    - Record Book 1866-1927 (Box 6)
    - Record Book 1952-1953 (Box 6)
  - Zoning Complaint 1990 (Box 6)
- Ministers' Files 1865-1990
  Ministers' Files includes correspondence and sermons of Charles Brigham in the 1860s through Kenneth Phifer in the 1980s and 1990s. The files of Harold Marley (1929-1942), Edward Redman (1942-1960) and Erwin Gaede (1961-1979) are especially abundant. Minister Marley's ACLU activity and his political convictions are well documented. Minister Redman's file contains copies of sermons broadcast on local radio stations during the 1950s as well as correspondence--arranged topically--on behalf of the Fund for Religious Freedom (a group opposed to the California Loyalty Oath for Churches) and regarding the Unitarian Student Group, for example. While both the Marley and Redman files contain some information on Gilbert House and their work with families at the Willow Run bomber plant, the researcher interested in those subjects should also consult a separate collection - Willow Run Area Recreational Project. Minister Gaede's correspondence, arranged chronologically, consists of almost a foot of material. Researchers interested in material on Minister Sunderland or his wife Eliza should be aware that the Bentley Library also holds their personal collections (see Sunderland, Jabez Thomas and Sunderland, Eliza Jane Read).
  - Charles Brigham
    - Pastoral record book 1865-1877 (Box 6)
      (includes list of contributions and Bible class members)
    - Memorial service 1879 (Box 6)
  - Jabez T. Sunderland
    - Biographical Materials Assembled by Alice Sunderland Wethey, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Writings and correspondence 1882-1929 (Box 6)
  - Harold Marley
    - Artwork by W.W. Nichols 1929 (Box 6)
      (pen and ink drawing of Huron St. church)
    - Writings and correspondence 1928-circa 1982, 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Writings and correspondence 1928-circa 1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - ACLU activities 1931-1935 (Box 7)
    - Eulogies by Harold Marley circa 1935 (Box 7)
    - Articles and news accounts 1927-1942 (Box 7)
    - Washtenaw Progressive activities, 1938-1940 (Box 7)
    - Scrapbooks of Published Articles
      - 1925-1945 (Box 7)
      - 1945-1960 (Box 7)
      - 1960-1972 (Box 7)
  - Edward H. Redman
    - Articles 1944-1946 (Box 8)
    - Attendance Graph 1945 (Box 8)
    - Building Blueprints undated (Box 8)
    - By-Laws and Policy 1944-1945 (Box 8)
    - Church Committees 1945-1949, undated (Box 8)
    - Civilian Chaplaincy Committee 1943-1945 (Box 8)
    - Democracy in Transition by Ralph Fuchs, Materials, 1955-1960 (Box 8)
    - Finances
      - Budget 1944-1945, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Quarterly Reports 1943-1958 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous 1949-1956, undated (Box 8)
      - The Unitarian Service Pension Society (Box 8)
    - George L. Jackson (Box 8)
    - Member Lists 1944-1952 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Area Council of Liberal Churches 1956 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Area Unitarian Council 1950-1952 (Box 8)
    - Midwest Unitarian College Seminar 1945-1946 (Box 8)
    - Midwest Unitarian-Universalist Ministers Association 1958-1959 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Sermons 1943-1985, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Public Relation Committee 1946, undated (Box 8)
      (includes membership pamphlet)
    - Pulpit Announcements undated (Box 8)
    - Sale of Church 1944-1946 (Box 8)
    - Transfers of Membership 1951-1960 (Box 8)
    - Willow Run Area Recreational Project
      - Correspondence 1943-1945, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Reports 1943-1944 (Box 8)
    - Unitarian Student Group
      - Administration 1944-1953 (Box 8)
      - Fair Employment Practices Committee 1945 (Box 8)
      - Programming 1945-1946 (Box 8)
        (includes surveys of students)
      - Student Lists 1943-1955 (Box 8)
  - Erwin Gaede
    - Correspondence
      - 1961-1967, 5 folders (Box 8)
      - 1968-1979, 10 folders (Box 9)
      - Letters of Support 1970 (Box 9)
    - Installation of Dr. Erwin Gaede 1961 (Box 9)
    - Politics and Ethics: Machiavelli to Niebuhr, 1983 (Box 9)
    - Sermons and other writings (Box 9)
  - Kenneth Phifer
    - Sermons 1994-1995 (Box 9)
    - Sock of Ages, poem by Jane Phifer, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Publications (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1906-1931 (Box 9)
    - Sermons undated, 3 folders (Box 9)
      (arranged alphabetically by title)
    - Sermons, miscellaneous and fragmentary (Box 9)